Good morning בוקר טוב Boker Tov we are on today's דף daf
is מכות ז Makkot Zayin we're at the משנה mishna on ז
עמוד א Zayin Amud Aleph is that right? Great.
Just want just double check. Okay.
This is going to talk about a someone who's been his been
convicted he escapes and then is found again. מי שנגמר דינו וברח
Mi shenigmar dino ubarach בא לפני אותו בית דין ba lifne oto
bet din אין סותרין את דינו. en sotrin et dino.
Someone whose דין din was finished so he was sentenced to some
sort of punishment וברח ubarach and he escaped ובא לפני אותו בית
דין uba lifne oto bet din he comes back in front of
the same בית דין bet din אין סותרין את דינו en sotrin
et dino you don't retry his case. כל מקום שיעמדו שנים ויאמרו
עדים אנו באיש פלוני שנגמר דינו בבית דין של פלוני ופלוני ופלוני
עדיו הרי זה יהרג. Kol makom sheya'amdu shenayim veyomeru edim anu be'ish
ploni shenigmar dino bebet din shel ploni uploni uploni edav harey ze
ye'hareg. So any case where two witnesses come and say we testify
באיש פלוני be'ish ploni to about such and such a person that
his דין din was finished he was sentenced to some kind of
punishment and it was in such and such a בית דין bet
din and such and this guy and that other guy were his
ראובן ושמעון Reuven veShimon were the עדים edim הרי זה יהרג harey
ze ye'hareg this person is put to death based on those two
people's testimony.
סנהדרין Sanhedrin this is a new topic סנהדרין נוהגת בארץ ובחוצה לארץ.
Sanhedrin noheget ba'aretz uvachutz la'aretz. A סנהדרין Sanhedrin of
seventy three סנהדרין Sanhedrin of seventy one seventy seventy
one seventy one is that right?
Seventy one seventy two twenty three also but judge local cases.
Okay so it's either seventy one or twenty three. Yeah based on
the גמרא Gemara it's going to be talking about twenty three.
So סנהדרין Sanhedrin of twenty three or בית דין bet din of
twenty three נוהגת בארץ ובחוצה לארץ noheget ba'aretz uvachutz la'aretz can be
set up whether in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael or outside of ארץ
ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. סנהדרין Sanhedrin
so this is a famous משנה mishna סנהדרין ההורגת אחד בשבוע נקראת
חבלנית Sanhedrin hahoreget echad beshavua nikret chovlanit sorry בשבוע beshavua נקראת חבלנית.
nikret chovlanit. A סנהדרין Sanhedrin that kills that executes one person in
seven years is called a חבלנית chovlanit destructive סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. רבי אלעזר
בן עזריה אומר אחד לשבעים שנה. Rabbi Eliezer ben Azariah omer echad
leshiv'im shana. רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Eliezer ben Azariah says one
in every seventy years. The גמרא's Gemara going to talk about whether
that means it's also called a חבלנית chovlanit or whether it's that's
an appropriate amount. רבי טרפון ורבי עקיבא אומרים אילו היינו בסנהדרין לא
נהרג אדם מעולם. Rabbi Tarfon veRabbi Akiva omrim ilu hayinu beSanhedrin lo
neherag adam me'olam. רבי טרפון ורבי עקיבא Rabbi Tarfon veRabbi Akiva say
if we had been in the סנהדרין Sanhedrin if we had been
in the proper בית דין bet din nobody would have ever been
put to death. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר אף הן מרבין שופכי
דמים בישראל. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer af hen marbin shofche damim
beYisrael. רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says that רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva and רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon by saying that are also increasing
bloodshed in ישראל Yisrael by saying we if you if the court
publicly states we never find anyone guilty then people are less afraid
to commit crimes and murder which apparently is not backed up by
empirical evidence which apparently is not backed up by empirical evidence. Okay.
So this is they're saying they should have a סנהדרין Sanhedrin with
the ability to have capital punishment even outside the land of ישראל
Yisrael whether there's a Jewish government or not basically. Ah so that's
the question so it's not it doesn't say בית bet it's you
set them up בין בארץ בין בחוצה לארץ ben ba'aretz ben bachutz
la'aretz doesn't necessarily mean where
right I guess בחוצה לארץ bechutz la'aretz do you ever have a
Jewish government?
I think if it's a Jewish I think it's saying if it's
a Jewish סנהדרין Sanhedrin in a couple of cases where Jews ran
things right but there is a note here it says that you
know first they need סמיכה semicha right? Second of all they could
only judge capital cases in the diaspora only as long as the
great סנהדרין Sanhedrin sits close down the
holy temple. So
as long as they were in any such times right right okay
right you have to have proper סמיכה semicha in order to even
have דיינים dayanim that can execute. To examples of Jewish monarchies where
after the... right. Okay. גמרא Gemara לפני אותו בית דין הוא דאין
סותרין הא לפני בית דין אחר סותרין. Gemara lifne oto bet din
hu de'en sotrin ha lifne bet din acher sotrin.
So the משנה mishna said that if the if the person who
escaped comes back in front of the same בית דין bet din
you don't retry him but so that implies that in front of
another בית דין bet din you would you would retry him. I'm
not sure what the logic is here about escaping and then being
allowed to retry your case
I'm not sure why escaping would like affect that. Question between you
know if there was new evidence between the time when he escaped
and when he returned.
Ah so if it's the same בית דין bet din even if
there's new evidence. That's my impression, I
don't know. Okay. הא תני סיפא, Ha tani seifa, כל מקום שיעמדו
שנים kol makom she'yaamdu shnayim ויאמרו ve'yomru מעידים אנו me'idim anu את
איש פלוני et ish ploni שנגמר דינו shenigmar dino בבית
דין פלוני ופלוני ופלוני עדיו beveit din ploni u'ploni u'ploni edav הרי
זה נהרג. harey ze neherag. That implies that you don't retry it
if two witnesses come and say we testify that this person's דין
din was finished, he should be put to death without a retry.
In any case, the note actually says if they don't reconsider sentences
to see if they can find new grounds for him. Right, so
again,
I'm not sure what the logic is in saying you escaped and
now you came back so we're going to try to find, I'm
not sure what the logic is in saying you escaped and came
back now we're going to try to find new evidence to acquit
you. It seems like if you escaped it's you still have you
still נגמר דינו. nigmar dino. So I'm not sure what the logic
is.
So the first, the רישא reisha seems to imply that only if
you go to the same בית דין Beit Din are you not
retried, but in any other בית דין Beit Din you would be
retried and you would try to find new evidence. But then the
סיפא seifa says if two witnesses come and say this person's דין
din was finished, this person was sentenced to death, he's put to
death immediately and they don't try to find new evidence. אמר אביי
לא קשיא, Amar Abaye lo kashya, this is not a difficulty. כאן
בארץ ישראל כאן בחוץ לארץ. Kan b'Eretz Yisrael kan b'chutz la'aretz.
The רישא reisha is in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, sorry, the
סיפא seifa is talking in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, the רישא reisha
is talking about outside of ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. So in ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael you would, if you came in front of a
different בית דין, Beit Din, you would try to find new evidence
to acquit. If he came in front of a different בית דין
Beit Din outside of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and you have two
witnesses to say that he is put to death, then you do
not retry.
דתניא, D'tanya, we have a ברייתא braita to support this. רבי יהודה
בן דוסתאי אומר משום רבי שמעון בן שטח, Rabbi Yehuda ben Dostai
omer mishum Rabbi Shimon ben Shetach, ברח מארץ לחוץ לארץ barach me'aretz
l'chutz la'aretz אין סותרין את דינו, ein sotrin et dino, מחוץ לארץ
לארץ m'chutz la'aretz l'aretz סותרין את דינו sotrin et dino מפני זכותה
של ארץ ישראל. mipnei zechutah shel Eretz Yisrael.
So the ברייתא braita says רבי יהודה בן דוסתאי Rabbi Yehuda ben
Dostai says in the name of שמעון בן שטח, Shimon ben Shetach,
if you escaped from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael to outside of ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael you do not retry a person if he comes
in front of a different בית דין, Beit Din, but if he
escapes from outside of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael to ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael you do retry the case because of the merit of ארץ
ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. רש"י Rashi says, it's not like sovereignty of the
court, it really undermines the justice system to some extent. רש"י Rashi
says, right, I was saying before I don't understand the appeal, I
don't understand the logic of just because you escape you get to
retry a case.
רש"י Rashi says, it's the first רש"י Rashi on the גמרא, Gemara,
מפני זכותה של ארץ ישראל, mipnei zechutah shel Eretz Yisrael, אולי תועיל
למצוא לו פתח של זכות. ulai toil limtzo lo petach shel zechut.
Maybe because of the merit of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael it will
somehow have an effect on the case and they'll find a reason
to acquit the escaped convict. I mean maybe to say that the
judges in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael might be more liberal or something
or they're like searching for leniency. Right, well it seems like the
better a דיין Dayan you are the more likely you are to
be able to find a reason for acquittal. So this if anything's
giving incentive for people to run away. Yes. It's a very I
don't understand the logic. Exactly, if you're מטהר השרץ metaher ha-sheretz you
ought to be able to be able to... Exactly.
So that's like what
רבי טרפון ורבי עקיבא Rabbi Tarfon ve'Rabbi Akiva were saying, אילו היינו
בסנהדרין, ilu hayinu b'Sanhedrin, like we are great Rabbis and we would
know how to find, we would always know how to find a
way to פטור patir someone who seems like they're guilty. Yeah, but
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says אף הם מרבים
שופכי דמים. af hem marbim shofchei damim. Exactly.
The same thing that we're doing here, letting someone run away from
outside ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael to ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and getting
a retry. Right. Yeah, so.
I'm not sure. Okay. סנהדרין נוהגת בין בארץ בין בחוץ לארץ. Sanhedrin
noheget bein ba'aretz bein b'chutz la'aretz. מנהני מילי, Mina hane milei, how
do we know this is true?
דתנו רבנן, D'tanu rabanan, והיו אלה לכם לחוקת משפט לדורותיכם, v'hayu eleh
lachem l'chukat mishpat l'doroteichem, it should be for you a statute and
a judgment for your generations.
צריך
לומר Tzarich lomar משפט לדורותיכם בכל מושבותיכם. mishpat l'doroteichem b'chol moshvoteichem. Ah,
it's supposed to say בכל מושבותיכם, b'chol moshvoteichem, in all of your
dwellings.
בכל מושבותיכם, b'chol moshvoteichem, למדנו, lamadnu, we learned לסנהדרין שנוהגת בארץ ובחוץ
לארץ. l'Sanhedrin she'noheget ba'aretz u'b'chutz la'aretz. All of your dwellings include those
dwellings outside of ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, so you set up courts
of twenty-three outside of
ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. אם כן מה
תלמוד לומר בשעריך? Im ken mah talmud lomar b'sharecha? If that's true,
why does the פסוק pasuk say בשעריך, b'sharecha, in your gates, which
usually implies in your gates in
ארץ ישראל? Eretz Yisrael? בשעריך אתה מושיב
בתי דינים בכל פלך ופלך. b'sharecha atah moshiv batei dinim b'chol pelech
u'pelech. בתי דינים batei dinim in
every district ובכל עיר ועיר u-ve-chol ir va-ir and in every city,
ובחוץ לארץ אתה מושיב בכל פלך ופלך ואי אתה מושיב בכל עיר
ועיר. u-ve-chu-tz la-aretz atta moshiv be-chol pelech va-pelech ve-i atta moshiv be-chol
ir va-ir. Outside of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael you set up a
בית דין Beis Din of 23 in every district but not in
every city. And what is a district?
A larger area. Like what, for example?
It's just
a province. Sure. I mean one בית דין Beis Din per state
like here or just every one בית דין? Beis Din? Yeah, something
like that. Like Manhattan and Queens. Right. I'm not sure who gets
to define what a פלך pelech is.
A country's divided up into provinces. Right. I'm not sure, I guess
the question is who gets to decide? I guess the בית דין,
Beis Din, maybe the סנהדרין Sanhedrin decides what a province is and
then they set up because it's the סנהדרין's Sanhedrin job to set
up the different courts. So they probably set up what a פלך
pelech is and they set up the province and then give a
בית דין Beis Din to it. Okay,
סנהדרין ההורגת אחד. Sanhedrin ha-horeget echad.
The משנה Mishna says סנהדרין ההורגת אחד בשבוע נקראת חבלנית. Sanhedrin ha-horeget
echad be-shavu'a nikret chavlanit. It's called destructive. רבי אלעזר בן עזריה אומר
אחד לשבעים. Rabbi Elazar ben Azariah omer echad le-shivim. Okay, איבעיא להו,
iba'ya lehu, אחד לשבעים שנה נקראת חבלנית או דלמא אורח ארעא היא?
תיקו. echad le-shivim shana nikret chavlanit o dilma orech ar'a hi? Teku.
So when רבי שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel, no, who
was it? When רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar ben Azariah said
one every 70 years, was he talking about that it's also called
a חבלנית chavlanit or was he saying that it's just אורח ארעא,
orech ar'a, that is the way of the world and that's the
way it should be, one every 70 years? תיקו, teku, let it
stand, we don't know an answer to that question. Well Israel is
70 years old and has executed through its court system one person.
Right, so it's time for a second one. Yeah,
Eichmann. Eichmann. He wasn't even Jewish. Right.
רבי טרפון ורבי עקיבא אומרים אילו היינו, Rabbi Tarfon ve-Rabbi Akiva omrim
ilu hayinu, if we had been in בית דין Beis Din we'd
never put anyone to death. היכי הוו עבדי, heichi havu avdei, how
would they have done such a thing? That's not a question of
morally speaking, that's a question of practically speaking. How would they be
able to פוטר poter everyone? רבי יוחנן ורבי אלעזר דאמרי תרווייהו, Rabbi
Yochanan ve-Rabbi Elazar de-amri tarvaihu, they both say, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
and רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar both say ראיתם טרפה?
הורג שלם הורג? re'item terefah? Horeg shalem horeg? Did you see someone
who was a טרפה, terefah, someone who
is deathly wounded, is going to... mortally wounded who got put to
death or did you see someone who was a שלם, shalem, a
complete person killed? אמר רב אשי, Amar Rav Ashi, ואם תמצי לומר
שלם, ve-im timtzi lomar shalem, if you do say that it was
a שלם, shalem, not a טרפה, terefah, הוה הוה, hava hava, if
that it was not a טרפה, terefah, דילמא במקום סייף נקב
הוה הוה. dilma bi-mekom sayif nekev hava hava. Maybe the place where
the sword went through the person is the same place where the
טרפה terefah was and therefore you actually don't know whether it was
שלם shalem or a טרפה. terefah. Everyone has a חזקה chazaka of
being...
Right, so the תוספות Tosafot bring up the problem that
by שחיטה shechitah we don't worry about this concern. I didn't get
to the answer in the תוספות, Tosafot, but I got to the
question. Yeah, but also for people, wouldn't we normally assume, don't we
operate on a presumption that someone is a שלם? shalem?
Right, so
the תוספות Tosafot say you have a... people have חזקה chazaka being
just like by שחיטה shechitah you have a חזקה chazaka of not
being a
טרפה. terefah. I mean clearly that can't be something we're worried about
because otherwise the תורה Torah can never say that you put anyone
to death.
Well that's the whole problem with what they're saying in the first
place, that we would have never put anyone to death. You're nulling
a law in the תורה, Torah, which happened. Yeah, they're basically abolishing
the death penalty. So then how
do the rabbis, even if they can do that, they ban... we
saw it by בן סורר ומורה, Ben Sorer u-Moreh, we saw it
by עיר הנדחת. Ir ha-Nidachat.
But giving the rabbi anything, it's a bit of a stretch. שופר
של ראש השנה שחל בשבת. Shofar shel Rosh Hashanah she-chal be-Shabbat. That's
a מחלוקת. machloket. The ירושלמי Yerushalmi thinks that really it's actually not
prohibited, it's not permitted anyway.
It's... the ירושלמי Yerushalmi seems to think that it's biblically prohibited to
blow שופר shofar on שבת Shabbat on ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah outside
the בית המקדש. Beit ha-Mikdash.
Something
conceptually happened with שופר shofar also. Okay, so it's a good question.
The תוספות Tosafot raise that question
another time I'll try to find the answer. Okay, בבא אל הערווה
היכי הוו? be-va el ha-erva heichi havu?
What about... okay so that's good for a case of a murder.
What about a case of... and here's the ריטב"א Ritva looking in
the middle. דחזקיה אמר באו נהרוג אדם מעולם לאו דווקא. De-Chizkiya amar
bau ne-herog adam me-olam lav davka. No, it's not really... you don't
mean that literally.
Most of the time they'll be able to get them off על
ידי
שמרבה בבדיקות, al yedei she-marbe be-vedikot, they're going to ask so many
questions שבסוף שלא יכחישו זה את זה, she-be-sof she-lo yakchishu zeh et
zeh, there'll be a הכחשה hachashah at some point. חברו, khaveiro,
you know, one will contradict the other.
That's what he says.
Oh right, I know and I remember. He says they say,
תוספות Tosafot say that
because if you ask a דיין dayan a question, if you ask
an עד ed a question and he doesn't know the answer
then it's possible that they become a פסול עד, pasul ed, that
all of their עדות edut doesn't happen if they say לא ידעינן
lo yadinan to say we don't know
and so that's what רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam says here. שפירש רבינו
תם בלא טעם הוא שכשאין שואלין להם ואין אנו יודעים אם טריפה
הוא או שלם נהרג חייב ובשביל שנשאל להם ואמרו אין אנו יודעים,
shepeirash Rabbeinu Tam belo ta'am hu shekshein sho'alin lahem ve'ein anu yodim
im tereifah hu o shalem neherag chayav uvishvil she-nishal lahem ve'amru ein
anu yodim,
if you ask and they say we don't know, יהיה פטור. yihiyeh
patur. The person who killed will become פטור. patur. לכן נראה דהא
דקאמר לא נהרג אדם מעולם לאו דווקא. lachen nirei de-ha de-ka'amar lo
neherag adam me'olam lav davka. Right
and that's why it's לאו דווקא. lav davka. And there
was a note about Michael's previous question about the טריפה tereifah status
that the majority
would not be considered to be טריפה tereifah but the implication is
that תוספות Tosafot is suggesting that
רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva are saying they
would continue to ask questions of minutia that would eventually trip up
the witness. Right right right. And then maybe you'd have one of
them say yes of course I know he wasn't a טריפה, tereifah,
the other one said oh maybe he is a טריפה tereifah and
then you have two עדים edim that are contradicting one another and
then they become פסול. pasul. Okay
we've got to move forward in the גמרא. Gemara. I sometimes learn
and maybe
it was only in civil cases that if the עדים edim disagree
on inconsequential details that that doesn't disqualify them. It makes them not
עדים זוממים, edim zomemim, but it still makes them עדים מכחישים edim
makh-khishim and they contradict and then they are פסול. pasul.
I believe
if they contradict one another they're not עדים זוממים, edim zomemim, they
don't get the punishment but they can still be פסול pasul if
they contradict each other.
That's what's implied. So they would ask questions until they contradict. Okay.
So that's fine for a murder case, what about a case of
בועל את הערווה, boel et ha-erva, someone who has illicit sexual relations?
היכי עבדי? heichi avdi? How would they do that? אביי ורבא דאמרי
תרווייהו ראיתם כמכחול בשפופרת. Abaye ve-Rava de-amri tarvaihu re'item k'mikhul bashfoferet. Did
you see the actual act of intercourse
like a mascara brush into a mascara tube? In other words the
actual act of penetration. That's used elsewhere. Yes it's a common metaphor
for sex. ורבנן היכי דיינו? ve-rabanan heichi daynu? And for the רבנן
Rabbanan how do they judge? כשמואל דאמר שמואל במנאפים משיכירו כמנאפים. ke-Shmuel
de-amar Shmuel bimna'afim misheyiru k'mna'afim. And the רבנן, Rabbanan, so that's a
problem for the רבנן. Rabbanan. How can the רבנן Rabbanan hold that
you can put someone to death for
ביאת ערווה biat erva if they don't actually require you to see
the penetration? Then you're not actually, then the עדים edim aren't actually
testifying about something they saw. And they say yeah it's like שמואל
Shmuel who said in a case of פריצות, pritzut, in a case
of illicit sexual relations, if you see them and they look like
they're doing it then that's enough.
You don't actually have to see the actual penetration. Okay. הדרן לך
כיצד העדים. Hadran lach keitzad ha-edim. I had a question on the
משנה. Mishnah. When we said the thing about מי שנגמר דינו, mi
shenigmar dino, when he runs away when he's לפני אותו בית דין
lifnei oto bet din and so on and then we answer this
to say that it depends on whether you run away from ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael or חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz to the other one.
But it says לפני אותו בית דין lifnei oto bet din though.
So I don't understand how you're explaining it that way. That it's
from not being לפני אותו בית דין? lifnei oto bet din? If
he's לפני אותו בית דין lifnei oto bet din in ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael then you're סותר. soter. If it's in front of a
different בית דין bet din in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and if
you're in front of a different בית דין bet din in ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael you're still סותר? soter? You're not סותר. soter. Then
what's אותו בית דין? oto bet din?
Sorry, in front of a different בית דין bet din in ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael you do not סותר. soter. Right. No, לפני אותו
בית
דין lifnei oto bet din in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael you do
not סותר. soter. Right. לפני a different בית דין bet din in
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael you are סותר. soter. לפני any בית דין
bet din? in outside of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael you are not
סותר. soter.
So in חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz you're never סותר soter the בית
דין bet din? even if it's a different בית דין? Beis Din
And in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael you, why
did we say that it depends on whether you're running away from
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael to חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz or vice versa?
No, that's just to support to say that it's different between ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael and
חוץ לארץ. Chutz La'aretz. So certainly if you run away from חוץ
לארץ Chutz La'aretz to ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael you would be סותר
soter the
בית דין? Beis Din You would be because they can't be אותו
בית דין oto bet din in that case. Right. And but in
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael but
it's just to show you the difference that חוץ לארץ. Chutz La'aretz.
And ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael are different דינים. Dinim. So the thing
is ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael has such a status that maybe חוץ
לארץ Chutz La'aretz would even in another בית דין din in ארץ
ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, even the first בית דין was in ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael too, but even another one would still manage to find
and make you find זכות Zechus to ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael just
does that. Exactly.
That's what we're saying. Okay. They say and I just thought רמב"ם
Rambam פוסק paskens according to the Rabbis that you do not need
to see the explicit act. Right. And that the שלחן ערוך Shulchan
Aruch goes as the רמב"ם. Rambam. Right. But the truth of the
matter is I mean
if this was like a capital case they would
carry out the case like right away and they put him in
jail anyway for like that little bit, right? So the most likely
wouldn't happen. Right. The only way this would happen is maybe in
a civil case somehow.
People do escape from prison. No, they're talking about here...
they're talking about adultery. No, I'm talking about the beginning of the
משנה. Mishnah. Oh, the first... Okay. הדרן עלך Hadran Alach אלא... Eila...
הדרן עלך
כיצד העדים. Hadran Alach Keitzad Ha'eidim. That is the end of the
first
chapter of מכות Makkot and we will now start the second one:
אלו הן הגולים. Elu Hen Ha'Golin.
We're going to talk about being
sent into exile if you accidentally kill someone in the Torah. The
Torah says you set aside ערי מקלט, arei miklat,
sanctuary cities, that if you accidentally kill someone you go to the
sanctuary cities. You go to the sanctuary city and there you are
protected from someone in the family of the person who you accidentally
killed is actually allowed to kill you. So if you go to
the עיר מקלט, ir miklat, then you are protected from that נקמת
דם. nikmat dam. You're protected from the comeuppance from that person. So
who are the people who are sent into exile? אלו הן הגולים.
Elu Hen Ha'Golin. These are the people who go into exile. הורג
נפש בשגגה, Horeig nefesh bishgaga, someone who accidentally killed someone.
It's weird that it says אלו הן Elu Hen since there's only
one category. Oh, no, sorry. There are more... there is a general
category and then there's specific instances. היה מעגל במעגילה ונפלה עליו והרגתו.
Haya ma'agel be-ma'agila venaflah alav ve'haragto. So you
are... according to רש"י Rashi explains this, they used to put pitch
on their roofs and they would have a log and they would
roll the log along the pitch to seal it and to make
it flat. So if you're pushing it and it fell and killed
someone then you are a הורג נפש בשגגה horeig nefesh bishgaga and
you are sentenced to
exile. היה
משלשל
בחבית ונפלה
עליו והרגתו. Haya meshalshel be-chavit venaflah alav ve'haragto. You are lowering a
חבית, chavit, you're lowering a barrel and it falls and kills
someone. היה יורד בסולם ונפל עליו והרגתו Haya yored be-sulam venaflah alav
ve'haragto
and you fall and you fall off a ladder and kill someone,
הרי זה גולה. harei zeh goleh. All of these cases are
sentenced to exile. אבל אם היה מושך במעגילה ונפלה עליו והרגתו, Aval
im haya moshech be-ma'agila venaflah alav ve'haragto, היה דולה בחבית
ונפסק החבל ונפלה עליו והרגתו, haya doleh be-chavit venipsak hachavel venaflah alav
ve'haragto, היה עולה בסולם ונפלה עליו והרגתו, haya oleh be-sulam venaflah alav
ve'haragto, הרי זה אינו גולה. harei zeh eino goleh. So if you
are pulling this roller thing up the roof and it fell and
killed
someone, or you are raising up this חבית chavit and the rope
broke and killed someone, or you are going up the ladder... Did
I say up the ladder or down the ladder before?
If you're going down the ladder and you fall and kill someone
then you are sentenced to exile. If you're going up the ladder
and you fall and kill someone then you are not sentenced to
exile. הרי זה אינו גולה. harei zeh eino goleh. You are not
sentenced to
exile. זה הכלל. Zeh haklal. כל שבדרך ירידתו גולה ושלא בדרך ירידתו
אינו גולה. Kol shebederech yeridato goleh veshelo bederech yeridato eino goleh. Any
case that you are going... it's דרך... derech... the way of going
down then you are sentenced to exile, and if it's not the
way of going down then you are not sentenced to exile. Is
he
פטור Patur altogether or he has to be tried? No, I think...
So we're going to deal with a lot of cases in the
גמרא Gemara also of people who are excluded from the case of
exile. I'm not sure in each case what the actual דין is.
I think in some cases I think it is that you would
have to pay damages
but you are not liable for the accidental
murder. And in other cases in the גמרא Gemara that it's going
to exclude from this category you are actually חייב chayav of מיתה.
misa. So the גמרא Gemara is going to... right. The גמרא Gemara
is going to exclude in both directions if that makes sense. What
was the case of מושך במעגילה, moshech be-ma'agila, what does that mean?
There's מעגל במעגילה ma'agel be-ma'agila which I understand, what's מושך במעגילה? moshech
be-ma'agila? There's מושך moshech is you're pulling it up. Pulling what up?
The מעגילה. ma'agila. I thought the מעגילה ma'agila was the one where
you were doing like
your
roof... So if I'm pushing it down the roof then I'm חייב,
Chayav, if I'm pushing it up the roof then I'm פטור. Patur.
Because it has to be דרך ירידתו. Derech yeridato. So one might
be liable for negligence, in other words, even if it wasn't intentional,
is that the... say it again.
It's an unintentional murder or killing, but the person might be liable
for negligence. Is that why he has to be... exactly. Exactly. I'm
not sure, so I think there are two aspects to עיר מקלט.
Ir miklat. One is the being protected from the person who's going
to kill you, from the family. I think another aspect is that
like when one accidentally kills someone else, there's like an... feeling
of
like you can't just like go back to your regular life. Like
that's a big deal. So even if you're not actually
obligated, you didn't intentionally kill someone, it's still like a...
you might have feelings of guilt, you might feel like you should
be punished. So I think that aspect is here as well, although
that doesn't quite work with the eliminating all of these different cases
of people who are not חייב Chayav to go into exile.
I guess maybe the difference between pushing it up and pulling it
down... pushing it up and going down is that
one... I'm not sure. Is the theory that taking it down you
should be more aware that it's likely to fall? I think so.
I think so. Especially in the case of... I mean, the case
of the חבית Chavit is the rope breaking.
But even if you're pulling it up and like it slips and
falls, it'd be the same thing.
You'd still be פטור. Patur. So I'm not sure.
Okay, so great.
גמרא. Gemara. מנא
הני מילי? Mena hanei milei? From where do we know all of
this thing about דרך ירידתו Derech yeridato versus
לא דרך ירידתו? Lo derech yeridato? אמר שמואל דאמר קרא Amar Shmuel
de'amar kra ויפל עליו וימת. Vayipel alav vayamot. I think it's ויפל
עליו וימת. Vayipel alav vayamot.
No, ויפול עליו וימות. Vayipol alav vayamot. And it fell on him
and killed him. עד שיפול Ad she'yipol until it falls דרך נפילה
Derech nefila the way of falling which is a downward motion. תנו
רבנן. Tanu rabanan. Now we're going to דרשן Darshen a bunch of...
we're going to take apart the פסוק, Pasuk, דרשן Darshen it word
by word. Do you have the
פסוקים Psukim there? Yeah. From במדבר? Bamidbar? Yep. Would you... sorry, yeah,
first, okay, yeah.
So the פסוק Pasuk says where is it here? I don't think...
35:23 is
for one
of them... בשגגה... Bishgaga... No, that's not בשגגה. Bishgaga.
Oh, there's another one later in... he's mentioned במדבר Bamidbar and דברים.
Devarim. Right, והקריתם
לכם
ערי מקלט Vehikretem lachem arei miklat and you'll split apart the cities
והקריתם לכם ערי מקלט Vehikretem lachem arei miklat and you'll call them
cities of refuge, ונס שמה רוצח מכה נפש בשגגה Venas shama rotzeach
makeh nefesh bishgaga and someone who kills accidentally kills someone else gets
to escape there. So the תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, the ברייתא Braita
says בשגגה, Bishgaga, the word בשגגה Bishgaga at the end of that
פסוק, Pasuk, פרט למזיד Prat le'mezid excludes someone who kills intentionally. בבלי
דעת Bivli da'at which is in דברים Devarim when it describes the
עיר מקלט Ir miklat there, it says without knowing, without knowledge, פרט
למתכוון Prat le'mitkaven is to exclude someone who intentionally kills someone. Right,
so it seems like they're the same. The גמרא Gemara is going
to pick up on that and redefine what each of them means.
מזיד פשיטא בר קטלא הוא. Mezid peshita bar katla hu. If someone
kills intentionally, it is obvious that person is excluded from going into
exile because he's חייב מיתה. Chayav mita. אמר רבא אימא פרט לאומר
מותר. Amar Rava eima prat le'omer mutar. Rather say that it excludes
someone who thinks that killing is permitted. אמר ליה אביי אי אומר
מותר אנוס הוא. Amar lei Abaye i omer mutar anus hu. Abaye
says back to Rava, if it's an אומר מותר Omer mutar that
person is an אנוס. Anus. We would not call that person... we
would not call that person מזיד Mezid in the ברייתא Braita because
it's not מזיד, Mezid, it's אנוס. Anus. It is... but he's not
אנוס, Anus,
I mean you killed them on purpose. Right, usually אנוס Anus means
forced, but in this case it also describes someone who is an
אומר מותר, Omer mutar, someone who thinks something is permissible. But in
any either case he's אונס ones and you would not the ברייתא
braita would not have called him מזיד. meizid. אמר ליה amar lei
אמר ליה amar lei Rava says back to Abaye שאני אומר she'ani
omer האומר מותר ha'omer mutar קרוב למזיד הוא. karov lemeizid hu. Someone
who's an האומר מותר ha'omer mutar is קרוב למזיד. karov lemeizid. Someone
who thinks that killing someone is permitted and they kill they're קרוב
למזיד, karov lemeizid, they're close to being an intentional killer הלכתית halachically
speaking. Therefore the ברייתא braita would call him מזיד. meizid. בלא דעת,
belo da'at, פרט למתכוין. prat lemitkaven.
The phrase בלא דעת, belo da'at, without knowledge, comes to exclude someone
who intends to kill. But if someone says אומר מותר omer mutar
then according to him he says קרוב למזיד, karov lemeizid, would you
actually kill that person? He says קרוב. karov. No, קרוב למזיד, karov
lemeizid, not מזיד. meizid. You would not that person would not be
put to death. But they wouldn't get... but they also would not
get גלות. galus. They would also not get גלות. galus. I think.
Right maybe it's let the relatives kill him or... could that be
like somebody who thinks somebody's a רודף rodef and was wrong? I
don't know that's a... would be a different case. I guess in
that right in that case you would sort of be an אומר
מותר omer mutar because you think it would be permissible even though
you're not but I think it's a different I think it's still
a different הלכתי halachic category than אומר מותר. omer mutar. אומר מותר
omer mutar thinks that it's permissible לגמרי legamrei whereas someone who acts
who kills someone who they think's a רודף... rodef... It's hard to
see how you could think it's permissible to kill someone. I know
that's what's so
strange. Yes, I
agree.
I mean we've seen the term I guess in the context of
מחלל שבת mechalel Shabbos in in terms of contemporary times. Right. But
that's a different that's a different thing. Different theory but. Right. Applying
it to murder is I'm not getting
it. It's
strange. That's yeah. Okay. The גמרא Gemara is now going to do
the same thing about מזיד. meizid. Sorry is going to do the
same thing about פרט למתכוין prat lemitkaven because that's also obvious that
that person is a בר קטלא. bar katla. So בלא דעת, belo
da'at, without knowledge, פרט למתכוין prat lemitkaven to exclude someone who intends
to kill. מתכוין פשיטא בר קטלא הוא. mitkaven pshita bar katla hu.
It's obvious that a someone who's מתכוין mitkaven is excluded because he's
also חייב מיתה. chayav misa. אמר רבה, amar Rabba, רבה Rabba says
פרט למתכוין להרוג את הבהמה והרג את האדם. prat lemitkaven laharog es
habeheima veharag es ha'adam. It's talking about someone who intended to kill
an animal and actually killed a person. לכותי והרג את ישראל lekuti
veharag es Yisrael or intended to kill a כותי Kuti and killed
a ישראל. Yisrael. ונפל והרג בן קיימא venafel veharag ben kayama or
he intended to kill a הלכתית halachically dead baby and killed a
viable baby. Yeah but in which case he doesn't get גלות? galus?
But we know that already. In which case he does not get
גלות. galus. Unless it's רב Rav because המתכוין להרוג זה והרג זה
פטור. hamitkaven laharog zeh veharag zeh patur. We had that whole thing
already. Right but you might say פטור patur from... פטור patur from
one thing חייב גלות. chayav galus. פטור ממיתה patur mimisa but you
don't. Right פטור patur from one thing חייב chayav for another but
also מתכוין להרוג זה mitkaven laharog zeh and not... although you'll notice
that this doesn't say מתכוין להרוג את ישראל והרג ישראל אחר mitkaven
laharog es Yisrael veharag Yisrael acher which means maybe that person is
actually חייב גלות. chayav galus. Okay another ברייתא braita with learning out
from these פסוקים. psukim. Excuse me. תנו רבנן, tanu rabanan, we learned
in a ברייתא braita ואם בפתע ve'im befesa if it is... excuse
me. Yeah sorry. ואם בפתע ve'im befesa if it is which means
ואם בפתע ve'im befesa how does that translate? Suddenly. That's what I
thought. If it is suddenly it says ואם בפתע ve'im befesa if
the death is sudden then that person is חייב גלות. chayav galus.
פרט לקרן זוית. prat lekeren zavis. That is comes to exclude a
corner which רש״י Rashi explains... קרן זוית keren zavis he explains שלשון
פתע הוא בסמוך. sheleshon fesa hu besamuch. The language of פתע fesa
implies that the two the one person who's killing the other person
are close to one another. בתקיף, betakif, they're immediately accessible to one
another. פרט לקרן זוית prat lekeren zavis to exclude a corner. אם
היה זה יוצא ממבוי זה, im haya zeh yotzei mimavoi zeh, one
person's coming out of an alleyway ונכנס לזה venichnas lezeh and he's
going into another alleyway לפנות לימינו או לשמאלו, lifnos limino o lismolo,
he's turning left or Right, and סכינו בידו sakino beyado and he's
holding a knife, וזה בא כנגדו ve-zeh ba kinegdo and someone comes
from the opposite corner בקרן זווית, be-keren zavit, ולא ראהו והרגו ve-lo
ra'ahu ve-hargo and they didn't see each other and he accidentally kills
him because he's walking with his knife outstretched, which is very irresponsible.
Yes, wait, so therefore what? Is viewed as, he doesn't get גלות?
galut? He doesn't get גלות galut in that case because they're not
close enough to one another ahead of time. But he's being very
irresponsible, in which case you'd think he's a higher degree of negligence.
Yes, he might. He probably has to pay damages, but he's not
חייב גלות. chayav galut. Whereas if he's walking just with his sword,
you know, straight, and then someone just walks out and then he
is חייב גלות? chayav galut? Yeah, if he's coming around a corner
or whatever. I think, I think, meaning there's no corner involved? The
corner is a mitigating factor, it seems, right? Yes. I think if
anything, the other way around, if he's walking around with his sword
outstretched, you know, and then he spears somebody, that's a very high
degree of negligence, right? And גלות galut shouldn't be the כפרה, kaparah,
right? Whereas if you're walking around a corner, that's an accident more
so. You know what I mean? Like that's exactly, oh my god.
Fine, if you're walking around with your sword outstretched, then you expect
people who are in front of you to see you. There's no
corner there. You expect everybody to be able to, you expect everybody
to be paying attention. You're saying he's still being negligent and therefore,
but you're not חייב גלות? chayav galut? Both people are negligent. In
this case, I guess both people have a level of negligence and
yeah. But in the case of the latter, you're saying that the
person, you know, the other guy who got killed has no negligence?
I'm, yeah, I don't know. See what I'm saying? Okay, yeah, I
get it. It's weird. It's a really weird case to say that
you're פטור. patur. So if like I shoot a gun, whatever, it's
like the same thing almost, right? I'm being negligent, the same thing
as the latter or something like that. You know, meaning if we
don't need negligence on both parties, just one of them... This seems
to be a very specific case, just walking around a corner and
one person accidentally stabs the other. I don't know what it says
about all these other cases you just brought up. בלא איבה, be-lo
eivah, the פסוק pasuk says without hatred ahead of time, פרט לשונא,
prat le-soneh, to exclude someone who already hates someone. I don't remember
if there's a רש"י Rashi here or not. No. But a שונא
soneh is considered to be, a שונא, soneh, if you hate someone
ahead of time you're not considered שוגג shogeg and you're not חייב
גלות. chayav galut. הדפו שדחפו בגופו hadafo she-dichapo begufo או השליך עליו
o hishlich alav להביא ירידה שהיא צורך עליה. le-havi yeridah she-hi tzorech
aliyah. Sorry, I read that wrong. הדפו שדחפו בגופו. hadafo she-dichapo begufo.
He pushed him, something was pushed, שדחפו בגופו, she-dichapo begufo, that he
has to push him with his body. בלא מתכוון, be-lo mitkaven, says
רש"י, Rashi, without intending to. Close, yeah, the whole thing is בלא
מתכוון be-lo mitkaven because פתע, peta, that's still part of it. Right.
או השליך עליו, o hishlich alav, or it is sent, it is
thrown upon him, להביא ירידה שהיא צורך עליה, le-havi yeridah she-hi tzorech
aliyah, to bring, to include in חייב גלות, chayav galut, a downward
motion that is, a downward motion that is needed, is part of
going up. Yeah, who cares? We know that a downward motion anyway
is just... But you might think that because it's part of an
upward motion, it's really part of on the whole as part of
an upward motion, then you might be פטור. patur. You're not. Like
if you're the example in the תורה Torah is an axe, right?
So if I have an axe, I want to swing it up,
in order to swing it up I have to bring it down
first. So you might think, oh, that downward motion is really just
part of the upward motion. No, it's חייב מיתה, chayav mitah, I
mean it's חייב גלות chayav galut in that case. שהיא צורך עליה.
she-hi tzorech aliyah. Okay, בלא צדיה, be-lo tzediyah, without, without forethought, right?
Without pre-trapping, without forethought of trapping someone. Prat, right, thank you, premeditation.
פרט למתכוון, prat le-mitkaven, that excludes someone who intended, sorry, פרט למתכוון
לצד זה והלכה לה לצד אחר. prat le-mitkaven le-tzad zeh ve-halchah lah
le-tzad acher. Someone who intends to strike or hit one side of
someone and actually hits another one, that person is not חייב גלות.
chayav galut. ואשר לא צדה, ve-asher lo tzadah, and he didn't have
premeditation, פרט למתכוון לזרוק שתים וזרק ארבע. prat le-mitkaven lizrok shtayim ve-zarak
arba. Someone who tried to throw something two אמות amot and actually
threw it four אמות, amot, that person is not חייב גלות. chayav
galut. ואשר יבוא... ve-asher yavo... Yeah, that's very, you know, which way
is that going? Is he's not negligent at all, or he's so
negligent that... I think he is, he is negligent but, he's negligent,
probably too negligent to be גלות. galut. Not negligent enough to be,
to be חייב גלות, chayav Galut, but you are חייב chayav to
pay damages I assume. And why? Meaning like, that’s, I think it’s
just standard. פרט למתכוין לזרוק שתיים וזרק ארבע. Prat le’mitkavein lizrok shtayim
ve’zarak arba. There’s a מחלוקת, machloket, oh, there’s a מחלוקת machloket about
how to read this ברייתא. braita. Every time it says פרט, prat,
does it mean פרט prat to include or is it פרט prat
to exclude? I think... No, פרט prat is always to exclude, right?
Doesn’t it mean like, you know, this and not that? Yes, but
there’s I think there’s still a מחלוקת machloket about how to read
this ברייתא. braita. I believe it’s a מחלוקת machloket between so someone
who right someone who intends to throw two and actually throws four
is פטור patur from גלות. Galut. ואשר יבא את רעהו ביער, Ve’asher
yavo et re’eihu ba’yaar, and they go, two people going together into
a forest. מה יער רשות לניזק ולמזיק להיכנס לשם, אף כל רשות
לניזק ולמזיק להיכנס לשם. Mah yaar reshut lenizak ule’mazik lehikaneis lesham, af
kol reshut lenizak ule’mazik lehikaneis lesham. Any place where both people have
permission to go is a place where being חייב גלות chayav Galut
to happen. The forest was not posted. Right, the forest was not
posted, there’s no no trespassing signs. מה יער, Mah yaar, just like
a forest, both the damaged and the damager have permission to go
to enter there, so too any location where the damaged where the
damaged and the damager have permission to enter. Okay. בעא מיניה רבי
אבאו מרבי יוחנן: היה עולה בסולם ונשמט השליבה מתחתיו ונפלה והרגה מהו?
כי האי גוונא עליה היא או ירידה היא? Ba minei Rabbi Abbahu
me’Rabbi Yochanan: Hayah oleh besulam venishmat hashleivah mitachtav venafelah vehargah mahu? Ki
hai gavna aliyah hi o yeridah hi? So someone is climbing up
a ladder and as when they push down on a rung and
then they lift their foot off and as they lift their foot
off or as they push down on the rung, the rung falls
and kills someone. Is that person חייב גלות chayav Galut or not?
The question is, is that a downward motion or is that an
upward motion? I thought we were talking about the person, you know,
I would say he’s פטור patur completely. Well, we already know about
a case where like the person falls off a ladder. We already
know the משנה mishnah tells us about a person falling off a
ladder. So this is a this is about the rung falling off
a ladder. ונשמט השליבה, Venishmat hashleivah, the rung falls. נשמט Nishmat is
removed, השליבה, hashleivah, the rung. I would say this person would be
completely פטור patur because meaning the משנה mishnah is talking about people,
so, you know, why would he even ask this question? What do
you mean? Climbing up a ladder, I step on the rung, the
rung breaks off and falls and kills someone. I understand. You think
I should be totally פטור? patur? Yeah. Why? Why should I be
חייב? chayav? Because I was negligent using a because my ladder, my
ladder is faulty. Who says I knew that? That’s what I’m saying,
I should maybe I should have known. Well, I didn’t know this
until I went on it and then it’s too late. You should
test it before, okay. והרגה מהו? Vehargah mahu? Or, or I should
make sure no one’s below me when I’m climbing up my ladder.
והרגה מהו? כי האי גוונא עליה היא, Vehargah mahu? Ki hai gavna
aliyah hi, is this going up, או ירידה היא, o yeridah hi,
or is this going down? Because you’re going up, but the rung
fell down. Okay. אמר ליה: כבר נגעת בירידה שהיא צורך עליה. Amar
lei: Kevar nagat biyeridah shehi tzorech aliyah. We already talked about this
in the ברייתא. braita. It said ירידה שהיא צורך עליה. yeridah shehi
tzorech aliyah. This would be pushing, your downward motion of pushing down
is down to go up, which is included, which the ברייתא braita
said is included in being חייב גלות. chayav Galut. No, that’s only
if you’re going... But remember the ברייתא braita said that a downward
motion that is לצורך עליה letzorech aliyah is is included להביא, lehavi,
it said להביא ירידה שהיא צורך עליה. lehavi yeridah shehi tzorech aliyah.
So the downward, in this case the downward motion is צורך עליה,
tzorech aliyah, but even so the ברייתא braita told us... But when
do you ever have an upward motion? Because you’re always pushing down
to go up. Right, yeah. You’re always pushing down to go up.
I know if I no, if I’m swinging my axe upwards... No,
for a ladder, meaning it’s always go what’s your so going up
is also pushing down on a ladder, is what I’m saying, right?
If I’m climbing down a ladder and I fall and kill someone...
If you’re climbing down the ladder, then you already know you’re חייב
גלות, chayav Galut, right? Right. And now if you’re going up a
ladder and the rung falls, we’re saying that’s also considered going down.
Because it’s a... Exactly, so it’s the answer to the question. So
whether going up or going down, you’re חייב, chayav, if a rung
falls out and kills someone. Whereas a person is different. If a
person is climbing up and falls down, then that’s different. I still
don’t understand. I don’t see the difference. Why should it be different
for the person versus the rung? Because the person’s going up. Yeah.
But he’s he’s going up, but he’s still pushing down on a
ladder I he’s still pushing down on the rung. His total motion
is upward. Okay. אמר ליה: כבר נגעת בירידה שהיא צורך עליה. Amar
lei: Kevar nagat biyeridah shehi tzorech aliyah. This is ירידה שהיא צורך
עליה. yeridah shehi tzorech aliyah. איתיבי. Eiteivei. He disagrees based on the
based on the based on the משנה. mishnah. זה הכלל: כל שבדרך
ירידתו גולה, שלא בדרך ירידתו... Ze hakk'lal: Kol shebederech yeridato goleh, shelo
bederech yeridato... שלא בדרך ירידתו shelo bederech yeridato לאתויי מאי? le'atuyei mai?
לאו לאתויי כהאי גוונא? lav le'atuyei k'hai gavna? Is it not, is
when the when the משנה mishna said שלא בדרך ירידתו אינו גולה,
shelo bederech yeridato eino goleh, that it's not בדרך ירידתו, bederech yeridato,
it's not in the matter of going down, is not exiled? Is
it not talking about this very case? ולטעמך ultamech says, I don't
remember who's talking here, Rabbi Abba? So Rabbi Yochanan says back to
Rabbi Abba, according to your reasoning, כל שבדרך ירידתו לאתויי מאי? kol
shebederech yeridato le'atuyei mai? Anything that is in the downward motion to
bring what? אלא לאתויי קצב. ella le'atuyei katzav. הכא נמי לאתויי קצב.
hacha nami le'atuyei katzav. Basically Rabbi Yochanan wants to read the final
phrase of the משנה mishna as having to refer to the similar
cases. So I think it's קצב katzav actually. דתניא... detanya... oh sorry,
I read that wrong. ולטעמך כל שבדרך ירידתו לאתויי מאי? ultamech kol
shebederech yeridato le'atuyei mai? Oh right, okay. So according to your reasoning
when you just said that the כל שלא בדרך ירידתו kol shelo
bederech yeridato is to include this latter thing then what would כל
שבדרך ירידתו kol shebederech yeridato come to include? It would also include
the same case of the ladder. It would come to include the
same case of the ladder and then it would be internally contradict
itself because it would include both, it would say that if you're
going up a ladder and a rung fell out then you're חייב
גלות chayav galut and it would say if you're going up a
ladder and the rung fell out you're not חייב גלות. chayav galut.
So it can't be both of those things. I'm still trying to
understand this whole case about the ladder and the rung. So like
if I'm okay, you know, if let's say I'm walking around with
my sword pointed out, right? And someone, you know, and someone just
whatever, you know, rounds a corner or something like that, you know,
and we say then one is... versus going straight. So what's weird
about the corner case now I'm thinking is that there's no דרך
ירידתו derech yeridato there, which is also strange. Yeah. So maybe that's
why he's פטור. patur. But in one case you said חייב, chayav,
right? Like, you know, so if I'm walking with my sword outstretched
and then someone was walking right up right to me and then,
you know, and I pierce them, right? Then was that חייב גלות
chayav galut or פטור מגלות patur migalut in that case? So there's
a ladder, climbing up, the downward motion. This has nothing to do
with the קרן זוית keren zavit case. No, I know, I'm asking
you though. In the case... and you'll see where I'm getting at.
Like so in the case where two people are coming, one has
a sword outstretched and the other just... and then he's חייב גלות
chayav galut if it's if they're both if they'll see each other?
Maybe. Or there's no downward motion, so maybe not. Forget the downward
motion. I can't forget that's an integral part of being חייב גלות
chayav galut is downward motion. No, but not in the case with
a sword. There's no downward motion there at all. Okay, so then
maybe you're פטור מגלות. patur migalut. No, but didn't we say... maybe
קרן זוית keren zavit is a... is just an example of a
case, because that... maybe קרן זוית keren zavit is just a case
where two people are walking and Rashi says this whole thing about
being קרוב, karov, but maybe... no, because of the word it used.
And it used בפתע befeta probably קרן זוית. keren zavit. פרט, prat,
which means you're not... which means it excludes the case of קרן
זוית. keren zavit. I don't know, but I want to... we have
to move on. ...running into each other, you'd be חייב גלות, chayav
galut, right? Possibly. So I buy a whole a brand new ladder,
right? Then I'm going up there, I've no reason to think anything
should happen and then the rung falls and I'm חייב גלות? chayav
galut? Yes. Why is it not completely an אונס? oness? I should
be completely... because you should make sure the area is clear. I
don't know. Maybe you put a sign up like that guy walks
and then... then maybe you're not חייב גלות. chayav galut. Maybe you're
not חייב גלות. chayav galut. We're going to come up to a
discussion about the two different ways of viewing the ladder. Okay, right.
What brought us to this? ולטעמך, ultamech, right, כל שבדרך ירידתו kol
shebederech yeridato לאתויי מאי? le'atuyei mai? אלא לאתויי קצב. ella le'atuyei katzav.
Rather it's to include a butcher. הכא נמי לאתויי קצב. hacha nami
le'atuyei katzav. So both כל שבדרך ירידתו, kol shebederech yeridato, כל שלא
בדרך ירידתו kol shelo bederech yeridato are to include a butcher. דתניא,
detanya, as we learn in the following ברייתא, braita, קצב שהיה מקצב.
katzav shehaya mikatzev. So a butcher who is chopping meat. תנא חדא
לפניו חייב לאחריו פטור. tana chada lefanav chayav leacharav patur. We have
one ברייתא braita that says if he's chopping down in front of
him he's חייב, chayav, if he's behind him he's פטור. patur. ותניא
אידך לאחריו חייב לפניו פטור. vetanya idach leacharav chayav lefanav patur. We
have another ברייתא braita that teaches the opposite. ותניא אידך בין לפניו
בין לאחריו חייב. vetanya idach bein lefanav bein leacharav chayav. And then
we have another ברייתא, braita, a fourth ברייתא braita that teaches the
opposite of that. ותניא אידך בין לפניו בין לאחריו פטור. vetanya idach
bein lefanav bein leacharav patur. ולא קשיא. velo kashya. כאן בירידה שלפניו.
kan biyerida shelefanav. One is talking about... every time it's talking about
חייב לפניו chayav lefanav it's talking about going down in front when
he's going down to chop the meat. ועלייה שלאחריו. va'aliya sheleacharav. And
going... so the first ברייתא braita where it says he's חייב לפניו
פטור מן האחריו, chayav lefanav patur min leacharav, he's talking about... the
blade falling out of the thing he's holding? I think so, yeah,
yeah, yeah. The blade is killing someone. So if he's פטור *patur*
if it's behind him and he's raising it up in order to
swing it back down, עליה של אחוריו *aliyah shel achorav* is פטור
*patur*. כאן *kan* the second ברייתא *braita* בעליה שלפניו *be'aliyah she'lefanav* is
פטור *patur*. He's lifting it up. Wait, wait, עליה *aliyah* you're פטור
*patur* if it's you're lifting it up? You're פטור *patur* if you're
lifting it up, because עליה *aliyah*... עליה לצורך ירידה *aliyah le'tzorech yeridah*
and you're חייב *chayav*? That's what we said that before, didn't we?
עליה לצורך ירידה *aliyah le'tzorech yeridah* is חייב *chayav*? No, ירידה לצורך
עליה *yeridah le'tzorech aliyah* is חייב *chayav*. שלפניו *she'lefanav* כאן *kan* בעליה
שלפניו וירידה שלאחוריו *be'aliyah she'lefanav ve'yeridah she'leachorav* lifting up in front and
going down behind, so there's basically four motions here. There's up, down,
up, down. So כאן *kan*, so it's going to basically every time
it says חייב לפניו *chayav lefanav* it's down in front, every time
it says חייב לאחוריו *chayav leachorav* it's down behind, every time it
says פטור לפניו *patur lefanav* it's up in front, and every time
it's פטור לאחוריו *patur leachorav* it's up behind. So basically the up
motions you're פטור *patur* for. Right, just like in any case, okay.
כאן בעליה שלפניו וירידה שלאחוריו *kan be'aliyah she'lefanav ve'yeridah she'leachorav*, כאן *kan*
the second ברייתא *braita* בירידה שלפניו *be'yeridah she'lefanav* going down in front
of you're חייב *chayav* ושל אחוריו ושל אחוריו *ve'shel achorav ve'shel achorav*.
Sorry, if you're חייב *chayav* both then it's down in front and
down behind, כאן *kan* and on the last ברייתא *braita* כאן בעליה
שלפניו ושל אחוריו *kan be'aliyah she'lefanav ve'shel achorav* going up in front
of you and going up behind you. In those cases you're פטור
*patur*. לימא כתנאי היא *leima katanai hi*. לימא כתנאי *leima katanai* maybe
this מחלוקת *machloket* between רבי אבהו *Rabbi Abahu* and רבי יוחנן *Rabbi
Yochanan* is like a Tannaitic dispute. היה עולה בסולם ונשמטה שליבה מתחתיו
*haya oleh besulam venishmeta shuliva mitachtav*, תני חדא חייב ותניא אידך פטור
*tanya chada chayav ve'tanya idach patur*. We have the very case, you're
going up a ladder and one rung falls out and kills someone
or does damage to someone. One person teaches חייב *chayav*, one person
teaches פטור *patur*. מאי לאו בהא קמיפלגי דמר סבר ירידה היא ומר
סבר עליה היא *mai lav beha ka miflegi de'mar savar yeridah hi
ve'mar savar aliyah hi*? One person says it is ירידה *yeridah* and
one person says it's עליה *aliyah*. And the person who says עליה
*aliyah* is פטור *patur*, the one who says it's ירידה *yeridah* is
חייב *chayav*. לא דכולי עלמא עליה היא ולא קשיא *lo dechulei alma
aliyah hi velo kashya*. Both we're talking about עליה *aliyah* and it's
not a difficulty, כאן לנזיקין כאן לגלות *kan lenizkin kan legalut*. You're
חייב *chayav* in נזיקין *nezikin*, you're חייב *chayav* to pay for the
damages, but you're פטור *patur* from גלות *galut* because it was עליה
*aliyah*. אי בעית אימא *i ba'it eima* or if you want to
say הא והא לגלות ולא קשיא הא דאיתליה הא דלא איתליה *ha
ve'ha legalut ve'lo kashya ha de'itlia ha de'lo itlia*. This one of
them is a case where the rung had some worms eating it,
so when you're stepping on the rung, before you actually push off,
it sags a little bit, so then it becomes a downward motion
and then it falls out. Therefore it's דרך ירידה *derech yeridah* and
therefore you're חייב *chayav*. And if it wasn't, but if it was
not then you're פטור *patur*, that's why that's the difference between these
two ברייתות *braitot*, one says חייב *chayav* and one says פטור *patur*.
אי בעית אימא הא והא לגלות ולא קשיא *i ba'it eima ha
ve'ha legalut ve'lo kashya*, sorry read that already. אי בעית אימא *i
ba'it eima* or if you want to say הא והא דלא איתליה
ולא קשיא הא דמהדק והא דלא מהדק *ha ve'ha de'lo itlia velo
kashya ha de'mihadek ve'ha de'lo mihadek*. That's my question, I buy a
new ladder and the rung falls off and I'm פטור *patur* no
matter which way I'm going, right? Unless it's not well, the last
one is if it's stuck in there well. So if it's not
stuck in there well then it's going to... then it's going to
do the same thing, it's going to sag and fall out and
then it would still be דרך ירידה *derech yeridah*. No, but if
I'm on a brand new ladder and it hits and kills somebody,
I'm going on my new ladder, it's perfectly fine rung, there's no
worms, no people around there. It depends on the way it falls
out. If it falls out because it's not stuck well and first
it sags and then it falls, then it's דרך ירידה *derech yeridah*.
But if it was a brand new ladder it wouldn't be sagging
presumably. Presumably. Although on metal, those metal ladders, the rungs always sag
a little bit when you step on them, I think it's part
of the design so they don't break. Although they're usually aluminum, so
nevermind. Aluminum. I didn't notice, which would not have been the case
in גמרא *Gemara*. Yes, that is true, that's also why worms would
be able to eat it because they're made out of wood. Oh
yeah. Okay. Thank you. Look, yeah, just my idea. Oh okay, thank
you.